CHANDU PULAPAKA

+13348957526 | cpulapaka7@gmail.com | Charlotte, NC, USA-28027 | LinkedIn

Professional Summary

Boasting over 3.5 years of experience in system architecture and full-stack development, this committed software developer specializes in cloud migration. Adept at using the Spring Framework's architectural patterns and coding languages to create microservices. knowledgeable about Agile processes and management systems, using advances with CI/CD using Docker, Kubernetes, and Jenkins, as well as test automation and runtime analysis. adept at creating guidelines and protocols to improve system functionality.

Technologies

SDLC, Agile Development, Waterfall Methodologies, Scrum
Java, Python, JavaScript, C#, C++
Spring (MVC, Boot, Security), Microservices, Node.js, React.js, AngularJS
JDBC, Servlets, JSP, JSTL, JavaBeans
HTML5, CSS3, HTML, TypeScript, Bootstrap, jQuery, Ajax, JSON, XML
RESTful APIs, GraphQL, SOAP
AWS, Azure, GCP, CloudFront, Azure SQL, Google Cloud
MySQL, NoSQL, SQL Server, DynamoDB, MongoDB
Dynatrace, Splunk, Grafana, Prometheus, Kibana
JUnit, Postman
Web Application Development, Software Development Methodologies, System
Design, Systems Design, Web Frameworks
Linux, Windows

Professional Experience

Software Developer

CitiusTech

USA, **01/2024** - Present

- Redesigned application architecture using microservices with Java and Spring Boot, enhancing scalability and improving sprint velocity by 33%.
- Enhanced cloud infrastructure on AWS (ECS, EC2) to reduce infrastructure costs by 25% while optimizing operational support.
- Developed responsive front-end interfaces with jQuery, React.js, HTML, and CSS, increasing user engagement by 45%.
- Performed load testing and performance tuning on Kubernetes clusters, improving response times by 15% and increasing environment consistency by 40%.
- Automated CI/CD pipelines using Docker, reducing release cycles by 20% for faster, consistent deployments.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to integrate back-end services with front-end applications, improving user engagement by 45%.

Software Developer

Intex Technologies

India, November 2020 - July 2022

- Built REST APIs for the CAM portal with the Spring Boot Framework, optimizing functionality and accessibility.
- Collaborated with a team of 7 during end-to-end development of a website. Leveraged **Python, Java, Docker**, and serverless framework while ensuring **continuous integration and continuous deployment (CI/CD)** with Jenkins.
- Improved test coverage from **50% to 80%** across microservices, with JUnit and PyTest, enhancing code quality and reliability while minimizing regression risks.
- Achieved a **20**% cost optimization by developing Python-based AWS Lambda functions to identify and remove stray EC2 instances, streamlining resource management and cost efficiency.
- Implementation scalability of microservices by deploying AWS components, including Amazon Lambdas and S3; improved application responsiveness under high loads while maintaining uptime for 99.9% of service requests.
- Architected scalable databases using **Oracle** and **MongoDB**, enhancing data retrieval speed by **35%** and reducing storage costs by **25%** through effective data compression and indexing.
- Enhanced user experience (UX) by optimizing front-end and back-end interactions, leading to a 20% increase in user engagement.

Jr. Software Engineer

Bytes Soft Solution

India, February 2020 - October 2020

- Influenced in Agile, contributing to sprint planning and retrospective meetings to ensure project alignment and timely delivery.
- Established Java-based web applications, achieving a **50%** reduction in load times and a **30%** increase in user retention while ensuring seamless scalability.
- Elevated application stability by integrating automated tests with JUnit, PyTest, and Jest; achieved a **35%** drop in critical errors and a **15%** acceleration in release cycles.
- Accomplished cloud infrastructure and deployment processes with AWS, and Jenkins, ensuring and solutions.

• Settled APIs using **GraphQL** and **SOAP**, enabling streamlined data querying and integration that improved response time by **30%** and reduced server load by **20%**.

Education

Master of Science

Auburn University at Montgomery

Montgomery, USA August 2022- May 2024

Major in Management Information Systems – GPA - 3.63/4

Relevant Course Work: Machine Learning, Leading Innovation, Enterprise Information Systems, Data Systems, Data Mining Methods and Applications, Data Analytics for Comp Advantages, Innovation Strategy, Information Security, Appl Bus and Data Analytics, System Analysis, Design & Implementation

Bachelor of Science

Vikas College of Engineering & Technology

Vijayawada, India, August 2017- July 2021

Major in Civil Engineering - GPA - 3.03/4

Relevant Course Work: Computer Programming, Engineering Workshop & IT Workshop, Probability and Statistics, Basic Electrical & Electronics Engineering, Surveying, Mathematics-I, II, III, Engineering Physics, Strength of Materials I & II, Managerial Economics & Financial Analysis, Project / Seminar/ Internship Project

Projects

System Analysis and Design for T-Mobile - Link

08/2023 - 11/2023

- Conducted system workflow analysis and created detailed process flow diagrams and data models using Microsoft Visio to streamline operations.
- Proposed system optimizations through data modeling and value chain analysis, leveraging SQL Server for efficient data management.

Smart Water Management System - Link

01/2024 - 04/2024

- Designed and implemented an IoT-based smart water grid system using Python and AWS, enabling real-time monitoring and efficient water distribution management.
- Developed system architecture diagrams and conducted data analysis to optimize water grid performance and ensure reliable operation.

Certifications

AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner

Microsoft Certified: Azure Fundamentals

Hands-On Java

Hands-On-SQL

Hands-On Linux

Managing Projects with Microsoft 365

Introduction to Career Skills in Software Development

Extra-Curricular Activities

- **Volunteered** in the **AUM Cultural Festival on April 6, 2024**, and participated in the Parade of Nations, representing my heritage.
- Secured 1st position in a Quiz Competition conducted on Engineers' Day on September 15, 20 at Vikas College of Engineering & Technology.